<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<root>

<!-- Each child of root should be an element named after the QT doc
     file name that will be needed (e.g. <overview> for
     overview.html).  Order of the elements matters and should be the
     order in which they would be displayed on a single page.
     Each child element of root should include the following nodes:

  <title></title> (navigation title for this content when it needs one)

  <intro><![CDATA[]]></intro>

  <mainBody><![CDATA[]]></mainBody>

  <outro><![CDATA[]]></outro>

-->

<overview>

  <title>Overview</title>

  <intro></intro>

  <mainBody><![CDATA[
<div class="note">
<h1 class="note_title">A Note On Floss Color Codes and Names</h1>
<p>
DMC and Anchor are well known manufacturers of floss (cross stitch
thread).  Each floss that DMC sells has a color name and numeric code
and each floss that Anchor sells has a numeric code, but neither DMC
nor Anchor provides color (RGB) values for their floss, so the colors
you see associated with numeric codes and/or color names in this
program are best guess approximations of the floss color associated
with a given code and/or color name.  Neither DMC nor Anchor endorses
these associations and neither has anything to do with this program,
nor does this program particularly endorse DMC or Anchor: they just
happen to be two common suppliers of floss.
</p>
</div>

<h1 id="overview" class="section">Overview</h1>

<p>
Cstitch turns an image into a cross stitch pattern and allows you to
edit the generated pattern.  The final product is a pdf of the cross
stitch pattern and a list of the colors in the pattern.
</p>

<p>
  The transformation is a four step process.
</p>

<div class="h2Div">
<h2>1. <a href="colorChooser"><i>Choose your colors</i></a>
<a href="colorChooser"><img src="colorChooser_active.png" alt="active color chooser icon"/></a></h2>
<p>
  There are three modes for choosing the colors to appear in your
  pattern, including choosing your own colors from the original image,
  choosing the number of colors you want to use and having the program
  choose the colors for you, and the option of choosing all of your
  colors to be colors actually available as floss.  If you choose your
  colors and later decide you're unhappy with your choice, you can
  either simply choose again or you can edit your choices by hand in
  step 3.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2Div">
<h2>2. <a href="colorCompare"><i>Compare color choices</i></a>
<a href="colorCompare"><img src="colorCompare_active.png" alt="active color compare icon"/></a></h2>
<p>
  At this stage your original image has been transformed into a new
  image using your color choices.  This step is used to compare your
  new image with the original image or with other color choices you
  have already made in order to decide which colors you'd like to
  move forward with.  If you decide to change your choice simply go back to
  step 1 and try again.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2Div">
<h2>3. <a href="square"><i>Square your image and edit</i></a>
<a href="square"><img src="square_active.png" alt="active square icon" /></a></h2>
<p>
  Your colored image has now been transformed into a "squared" or
  "grided" image as in the final cross stitch pattern.  Here you can
  edit your pattern by changing colors and freehand drawing until
  you're satisfied.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2Div">
<h2>4. <a href="pattern"><i>Create the pattern and edit</i></a>
<a href="pattern"><img src="pattern_active.png" alt="active pattern icon" /></a></h2>
<p>
The squared color image has now had colors replaced with symbols,
which you can change from among those available.  When you're
satisfied with the symbols, save your pattern to a pdf.
</p>
</div>

<h1>Moving Between the Stages</h1>
<p>
 Each of the four stages has its own panel; to move between the panels
 (as they become available), you can either use the the sequence of
 four icons (shown above) that appears on the right side of the
 toolbar, or you can choose from the <i>Windows</i> menu.  The current
 panel's icon will always appear highlighted with a green border and
 those that haven't been activated yet will appear grayed out.
</p>

<h1>Zooming</h1>

<p>
The first three stages provide two sets of zooming operations.
The first set appears on the toolbar (and also from the <i>Image</i>
menu) and consists of a "Zoom to fit" option <img
src="zoomToImage.png" alt="zoom to image icon"/> that zooms the image to be as large as
possible and still fit in the available space, a "Zoom to width"
option <img src="zoomToWidth.png" alt="zoom to width icon" /> that zooms the image to fit the
available width, a "Zoom to height" option <img src="zoomToHeight.png" alt="zoom to height icon"
/> that zooms the image to fit the available height, and an "Original
size" option <img src="zoomToOriginal.png" alt="zoom to original icon" /> that zooms the image to
its original size.  (There's a caveat for square images - see <a
href="square#zoom_caveat">this</a> for details.)
</p>

<p>
The second set of zoom options is available from the <i>Image</i> menu
and consists of a "Zoom in" option <img src="zoomIn.png" alt="zoom in icon" /> that
increases the zoom by a fixed amount and a "Zoom out"
option <img src="zoomOut.png" alt="zoom out icon" /> that decreases the zoom by a fixed
amount.
</p>

<p>
In the last (pattern) stage, only the second set of options is
available, either from the toolbar or from the <i>Image</i> menu.  At
the pattern stage the zoom level of the image determines the size of
the symbols in the pdf pattern output, i.e. the size of a square in
the pdf pattern will be (approximately) the same size as a square
on the screen.  In all other stages the zoom level has no effect on
processing.
</p>

<h1>Saving images</h1>
<p>
You can save the active image at any time as a jpg, png, pdf, or any
of several other formats, by clicking on the save
icon <img src="saveImage.png" alt="save image icon" /> on the toolbar or by choosing <i>Save
Image</i> from the <i>File</i> menu (not available from the first
panel since the only image there is the original!).
</p>

<p><b>Note: </b>Saving an image does <b>not</b> allow you to restore
that image after you've quit the program.  For that, read on to the
next section on saving projects.
</p>

<p><b>Technical Note: </b>Square and pattern images (from the square
edit and pattern edit stages) are handled internally by this program
in a way that makes it easy to zoom to very large sizes on screen
without using many resources, but if you request to <em>save</em> such
an image, then the program must request enough memory to hold the
entire image all at once.  At very large zoom levels this can require
requesting and working with a gigabyte or more of memory which,
depending on your computer's resources, could take anywhere from a
couple of seconds to tens of minutes for your computer to process,
leaving your computer bogged down in the meantime.
</p>
<p>
A warning message will appear if you attempt to save a large file,
telling you how much memory will be required, and you can then decide
whether to go ahead with the save or to cancel.  To be safe, if you
get such a warning and decide to save the image, you should first save
your project.
</p>

<h1 id="saveRestore">Saving and restoring projects</h1>
<p>
You can save your work at any time by clicking on the save project
icon <img src="saveProject.png" alt="save project icon" /> on the toolbar or by
choosing <i>Save Project</i> (or <i>Save Project As</i>) from
the <i>File</i> menu.  "Project" here refers to all of the images in
all of the panels, as well as various settings in those panels.  We
reccomend saving your project with a .xst extension (myProject.xst,
for example), but you can use any filename you'd like, with or without
an extension.
</p>

<p><b>Note: </b>The only image contained in a saved project file is the
original image that started the project; all other images associated
with the saved project are restored from the original when the project
is reloaded.  This keeps project files small and portable, but means
longer load times spent regenerating images.  (That means that if
you've created images that you know you aren't going to use, it's best
to delete them before saving your project.)
</p>

<p>
To restore your work from a saved project file, just click on the open
project icon <img src="openProject.png" alt="open project icon" /> on the toolbar or
choose <i>Open Project</i> from the <i>File</i> menu and open the
project file you saved above.
</p>

<h1 id="overview_keyboard_shortcuts">Keyboard shortcuts</h1>
<p>
In addition to keyboard shortcuts listed in the menus, you can press
"Ctrl+Enter" (i.e. hold down the control key and then press enter) at
any time to process the current stage and move on to the next.  Other
panel-specific keyboard shortcuts are
listed <a href="colorCompare#color_compare_keyboard_shortcuts">here</a>
for the color compare panel,
<a href="square#square_keyboard_shortcuts">here</a> for the square edit
panel, and
<a href="pattern#pattern_keyboard_shortcuts">here</a> for the pattern
edit panel.
</p>

<h1>Panel specific help</h1>
<p>
Selecting "Help" from the Help menu will always display help for
whichever of the four panels you're currently on.
</p>
]]></mainBody>

  <outro><![CDATA[
<div class="h2Div"><a href="colorChooser"><i>The color chooser panel</i></a></div>
<div class="h2Div"><a href="colorCompare"><i>The color compare panel</i></a></div>
<div class="h2Div"><a href="square"><i>The square edit panel</i></a></div>
<div class="h2Div"><a href="pattern"><i>The pattern edit panel</i></a></div>
]]></outro>

</overview>

<!--##################################################################-->

<colorChooser>

  <title>Color Chooser</title>

  <intro><![CDATA[
<h1>New User?</h1>
<p>
If you're a new user, you may want to start with
the <a href="overview">Overview</a> before continuing with
this documentation for the <i>Color Choosing Panel</i>.
</p>

<h1>A Note On Floss Color Codes and Names</h1>
<p>
DMC and Anchor are well known manufacturers of floss (cross stitch
thread).  Each floss that DMC sells has a color name and numeric code
and each floss that Anchor sells has a numeric code, but neither DMC
nor Anchor provides color (RGB) values for their floss, so the colors
you see associated with numeric codes and/or color names in this
program are best guess approximations of the floss color associated
with a given code and/or color name.  Neither DMC nor Anchor endorses
these associations and neither has anything to do with this program,
nor does this program particularly endorse DMC or Anchor: they just
happen to be two common suppliers of floss.
</p>
</div>
]]>
  </intro>

  <mainBody><![CDATA[
<h1 id="colorChooser" class="section">The Color Choosing Panel
<img src="colorChooser_active.png" alt="active color chooser icon" /></h1>

<p>
Start a new project by opening a saved image from your files, either
by clicking the folder icon <img src="openImage.png" alt="open image icon" /> on the toolbar
or choosing <i>Open</i> from the <i>File</i> menu.
</p>

<p>
The purpose of this first step is to reduce the number of colors in
your image (typically hundreds of thousands) to a (typically much
smaller!) selection of colors that you'd like to use as floss colors
for the final pattern.  The manner in which that is accomplished is
determined by the "color selection mode", described next.
</p>

<div class="h2Div">
<h2 id="colorSelectionMode">Choosing the Color Selection Mode</h2>
<p>
The color selection mode is chosen from the dropdown box on the
toolbar.  There are three modes to choose from:
</p>
</div>

<div class="h3Div">
<h3><i>Num colors to DMC [default]</i></h3>

<p>
In this mode the number of colors chosen is determined by two
processes: user selection and program selection.  User selection works
by clicking on a color in the original image: the program will
transform the clicked color into the closest matching DMC color and
add the DMC color to the <i>Clicked colors</i> list on the right hand
side of the window.  The other color selection process is done by the
program: set the <i>number</i> of DMC colors you would like the
program to choose from the box to the right of the <i>Color Selection
Mode</i> box.
</p>
<p>
The colors the program chooses are based on the frequency with which
colors in the original image appear, so it's possible that small but
important features (such as eye color, for example) may not have the
desired color after this step (this program can't recognize features
in your image, only colors).  Such features can be corrected by hand
in <a href="square">a later step</a>.  The program will choose
its colors so that there is no overlap with any colors you choose by
clicking.  <b>Thus the total number of colors chosen will be the sum
of the user-clicked colors and the number of program-selected
colors.</b>
</p>
<p>
The program chooses its colors when you click on the <i>Process</i>
button on the toolbar.  The list of all colors chosen will appear to
the right of the image at the next stage, or you can return to this
stage at any time to see the list of program chosen colors in
the <i>Generated colors</i> list to the right of the image.
</p>
<p>
<b>Note: </b>The major advantage of using the <i>Num colors to DMC</i>
mode is that it is guaranteed to produce colors that are available as
floss.  The disadvantage is that the colors selected all come from the
fixed pool of DMC colors (currently 428 colors).  One consequence is
that there may be no way to choose close shades of color from your
original image unless similar close shades already exist as DMC
colors.  The next mode gets around that by allowing you to select
exact colors from the original image (which may not be available as
floss!).
</p>
</div>

<div class="h3Div">
<h3><i>Num colors to Anchor</i></h3>
<p>
This mode works exactly the same as the <i>Num colors to DMC</i>
mode, except it creates Anchor colors instead of DMC colors.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h3Div">
<h3><i>Num colors</i></h3>
<p>
This mode is similar to <i>Num colors to DMC</i> mode, except that any
color you click on will be added directly to the <i>Clicked colors</i>
list without being transformed to a DMC color first, and the colors
chosen by the program will all be colors actually occurring in the
image.
</p>
<p>
While this mode will generally result in new images that match the
original more closely than <i>Num colors to DMC</i> mode, the
disadvantage is that the colors used to produce the new images may not
be available as floss colors.  Nonetheless, you may want to use this
mode to produce an image to be used as the basis for adjusting the
results of a DMC-mode image.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h3Div">
<h3><i>DMC</i></h3>
<p>
<i>DMC</i> mode will create a new image by replacing each color in
your original image with the closest matching DMC color.  This
program is aware of 428 DMC color names, so depending on
the variety of colors in your original image, this mode can create a
new image with anywhere from 1 to 428 colors.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h3Div">
<h3><i>Anchor</i></h3>
<p>
<i>Anchor</i> mode works the same as <i>DMC</i> mode except that it
creates Anchor colors instead of DMC colors.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2Div">
<p>
<b>Note: </b>The colors produced in this step aren't guaranteed to be
in the final image - chosen colors that appear relatively infrequently
could be removed by further processing at a later stage.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2Div">
<h2>Proceeding to the Color Compare Panel</h2>
<p>
After you have chosen the <i>Color Selection Mode</i> and your colors
(or number of colors), click the <i>Process</i> button to continue to
the next step, the <a href="colorCompare"><i>Color Compare
Panel</i></a>.  You can come back to this panel, change your selection
mode, and click <i>Process</i> as many times as you want, and each
processed image will be available in the next panel, where you can
compare results.
</p>

<p>
<b>Note: </b>This <i>color choosing</i> step performs mostly
automated color selection.  A <a href="square">later</a> step
will allow for editing "by hand" to change/add/delete colors.
</p>
</div>
]]></mainBody>

  <outro><![CDATA[]]></outro>

</colorChooser>

<!--##################################################################-->

<colorCompare>

  <title>Color Compare</title>

  <intro><![CDATA[]]></intro>

  <mainBody><![CDATA[

<h1 id="colorCompare" class="section">The Color Compare Panel
<img src="colorCompare_active.png" alt="active color compare icon" /></h1>

<p>
The color compare panel allows you to compare your new image with the
original image and other images created from the <i>Color Chooser
Panel</i>.
</p>

<p>
This panel can show two images side by side; to choose which image is
shown on a given side, left or right, either choose from the
appropriate pull-down list on the toolbar (labelled <i>L:</i>
or <i>R:</i>), or choose from the list in the appropriate <i>Left
Image</i> or <i>Right Image</i> menu.  (You can't view the same image
on both sides, so you will only be able to change a side if you have
created more than one image from the <i>Color Chooser Panel</i>.)
</p>

<div class="h2Div">
<h2>Hiding and Showing Images</h2>
<p>
You can hide an image by unchecking the <i>Show image</i> box in the
appropriate left or right image menu - hiding one image will give the
other image as much room as possible.  Recheck the box to reshow the
image.
</p>

<p>
You can manually give one side of the viewer more room by dragging the
middle bar of the viewer to one side or the other.  To reset the bar
to the center, click on <i>Center splitter</i> in the <i>Image</i>
menu.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2Div">
<h2>Deleting Images</h2>
<p>
If you choose <i>Delete image</i> from one of the image menus, the
image cannot be recovered.  You can't delete the original image.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2Div">
<h2 id="color_compare_keyboard_shortcuts">Keyboard shortcuts</h2>
<p>
You can press "Shift + Left Arrow" (i.e. hold down the shift key and
then press the left arrow key) to make the left image active, "Shift +
Right Arrow" to make the right image active, "Shift + Up Arrow" to
move up in the image list for the active side, and "Shift + Down
Arrow" to move down in the image list for the active side.  The same
shortcuts apply in the square edit panel.
</p>
<p>
See the <a href="overview#overview_keyboard_shortcuts">overview</a>
for application-wide keyboard shortcut information.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2Div">
<h2>Dual Scrolling</h2> 
<p>
By default, if scrollbars are necessary for
your images, scrolling one side will automatically scroll the other
side by the same amount.  You can turn this behavior off or on by
unchecking or checking the <i>Dual scrolling</i> box from
the <i>Image</i> menu.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2Div">
<h2>Dual Zooming</h2> 
<p>
By default, zooming the active image will apply the same zooming to
the inactive image.  You can turn this behavior off or on by
unchecking or checking the <i>Dual zooming</i> box from the
<i>Image</i> menu.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2Div">
<h2>Selecting the Squaring Parameters</h2> 
<p>
The processing that occurs in this step turns a smoothly colored image
into a "squared" image, as in the final pattern, where each square in
the image has just one color.  The manner in which the current image
is tranformed into a squared/patterned image depends on
the <i>squaring mode</i> and the <i>square size</i> setting.
</p>

<p id="squareSize">
The <i>square size</i> setting determines how
large (in pixels) the squares to be created will be.  The size is set
using the number box on the toolbar, and is allowed to have any value
from 2 to 50.  The choice of square size, along with your choice of
cross stitch fabric, will determine how large your final cross
stitched piece will be - click on the <i>Dimension Computer</i> icon
<img src="dims.png" alt="dimension computer icon" /> on the toolbar to
help you choose the correct square size based on your fabric type and
your desired final dimensions.
</p>

<p>
The color that goes in a particular box of the pattern image (referred
to as the <i>representative color</i> of that block below) is
determined by the <i>squaring mode</i>, for which there are two
possible values.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h3Div">
<h3>1. Median Mode [default]</h3> 
<p>
Under median mode, roughly speaking, the representative color of a
given block is chosen to be that color in the block that is "least
far" in total from all of the other colors in the block.  This can be
thought of as choosing the "most representative" color in a given
block, and generally gives the best results.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h3Div">
<h3>2. Mode Mode</h3>
<p>
Mode mode chooses the representative color of a given block to be the
color that appears most often in that block.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2Div">
<h2>Proceeding to the Square Editing Panel</h2>
<p>
 Once you have chosen the <i>squaring mode</i> and <i>square</i>
size, <b>click on the image you wish to square</b> to select it and
then click the <i>Square</i> button on the toolbar, which will take
you to the <a href="square">Square Editing Panel</a>.  
</p>

<p>
You can return to this panel, change your options, and click Square as
many times as you like.
</p>
</div>
]]></mainBody>

  <outro><![CDATA[]]></outro>

</colorCompare>

<!--##################################################################-->

<square>
  
  <title>Square</title>

  <intro><![CDATA[]]></intro>

  <mainBody><![CDATA[

<h1 id="square" class="section">The Square Edit Panel
<img src="square_active.png" alt="active square icon" /></h1>

<p>
The square edit panel allows you to edit your pattern by changing
colors and freehand drawing.
</p>

<div class="h2">
<h2 id="squareTools">Square Pattern Editing Tools</h2>
<p>
This panel provides four tools for editing your pattern by hand.
</p>
<p>
<b>Note: </b>You can't edit the original image using these tools, but
you can use the tools to choose colors from the original image.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h3">
<h3>Selection mode <img src="cursor.png" alt="cursor icon" /></h3>
<p>
Click on the selection mode icon to be able to select an image with
the mouse (if other tools are active, a mouse click may mean something
else) - basically selection mode provides what you would think of as
standard mouse behavior, as opposed to the other tools.
</p>
<p>You can also select the left or right image at any time by using
the left image button <img src="leftImage.png" alt="left image icon" /> or the right image
button <img src="rightImage.png" alt="right image icon" /> on the toolbar.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h3">
<a name="change_a_color_tool"></a>
<h3>The Change a Color Tool <img src="changeAll.png" alt="change all icon" /></h3>
<p>
Use this tool to change a color in your image.  You can also change a
color by right clicking on it at any time in the color list and
choosing <i>Change color</i>.
</p>

<p>The color to be changed <i>to</i> is displayed in a color swatch
above the tools.  You can set that color in any of four ways:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Right click on a color on either image;</li>
<li>Middle click on either image to open the Color Dialog to choose a
color (with initial choices based on the colors in the image around
where you clicked) - see below for more information on the Color
Dialog options;</li>
<li>Click on the color swatch to set an arbitrary color;</li>
<li>Right click on the color you want in the color list and
choose <i>Set as tool color</i>.</li>
</ul>

<p>
Once the swatch color has been set, left click on a color in the
selected image to change it to the swatch color.
</p>
</div>

<div style="margin-left: 40px;">
<div class="h2">
<h2>The Color Dialog</h2>

<p>
The color dialog offers up to five ways to choose a new color; you can
alternate between the options using the menu in the lower left corner
(depending on settings and situation some options may not be available).
</p>

<p>
The combo box below the tools can be used to restrict the type of
colors that can be chosen using the color dialog: choose "DMC colors
only" or "Anchor colors only" to restrict to colors of type DMC or
Anchor, respectively.
</p>

<div class="h3">
<h3>Choose a Square Color</h3> 
<p>
If the square you click on contains more than one color <i>in the
original image</i> then this mode will allow you to choose from the
colors from the original image in the clicked square.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h3">
<h3>Choose a List Color</h3>
<p>
Choose a color from those already present in the image.  The original
color clicked on is in the upper left hand corner and the rest of the
colors are arranged by rows from nearest to furthest from the original
color.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h3">
<h3>Choose a DMC Color</h3> 
<p>
With this option you can choose any DMC
color; colors are arranged in the same manner as for the <i>Choose a
List Color</i> option.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h3">
<h3>Choose n Anchor Color</h3> 
<p>
With this option you can choose any Anchor
color; colors are arranged in the same manner as for the <i>Choose a
List Color</i> option.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h3">
<h3>Choose From an Image</h3>
<p>
This option allows you to choose a color from any image currently on
view in the main panel.  The color block is arranged as follows: the
large rectangle on the left is the original color, the upper right
square is the most recently clicked color, and the lower right square
is the color the mouse is currently over.  Click on the new color you
want from an image and then click the <i>Accept</i> button to confirm
your choice - if you misclick simply click on a different color before
hitting the Accept button.
</p>
<p>
If you're in DMC only or Anchor only mode then the upper right square will always be
translated to a DMC or Anchor color, respectively.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h3">
<h3>Choose a New Color</h3>
<p>
Use this option to choose a color from a color palette or by providing
an RGB or HSV value. 
</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>

<div class="h3">
<h3>The Draw Tool <img src="draw.png" alt="draw icon" /></h3>
<p>
Use the draw tool to freehand draw on your image by holding down the
left mouse button while dragging the mouse.  The drawing color is
displayed in the color swatch above the tools.  You can set it as
described under the <i>Change a color tool</i> directions.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h3">
<h3>The Fill Region Tool <img src="fill.png" alt="fill icon" /></h3>
<p>
Use the fill region tool to change the color of a specific region in
the image by left clicking in the region.  The new color is determined
just as for the <i>Change a color tool</i>.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h3">
<h3>The Detail Tool <img src="detail.png" alt="detail icon" /></h3>
<p>
The detail tool is intended to be used to restore color to small
detail areas of an image that may not have received adequate treatment
from prior automated processing (the automated processing concentrates
mostly on picking out the most prominent colors).
</p>

<p>
To use the tool, left click/drag on the selected image over the region
you'd like to detail.  As you drag, the squares under the mouse will
be marked with xes.  To unmark individual marked squares, right
click/drag on the square(s), or click on the <i>Clear</i> button to
clear all of the marked squares.<br />
<b>Note: </b>The tool works best if you concentrate on individual
features you'd like to restore, i.e. it's better to mark and detail many
smaller regions of similar colors than to mark a single larger region
with many mixed features/colors.
</p>

<p>
The <i>Colors</i> selection box determines the maximum number of
colors that will be used to recolor the area that you've marked.  Once
you've marked an area and chosen the number of colors you'd like to
use, click the <i>Detail</i> button.  The new colors for the marked
region will be chosen from the colors on the original image in that
region, or DMC/Anchor versions of those colors if the <i>DMC/Anchor
colors only</i> option is set.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2">
<h2>Replace Rare Colors</h2>
<p>
Although this program makes an attempt to choose only colors that
appear frequently in the original image, you may still wind up with
several colors that appear in only a few squares in your square image.
To replace such colors with colors that appear more frequently,
choose <i>Replace rare colors</i> from the <i>Image</i> menu.  The
dialog that pops up allows you to define what &ldquo;rare&rdquo;
means in the top line, and then lists the rare colors in the image
along with the number of squares each occupies and what color (from
among the &ldquo;common&rdquo; colors already in the image) it will be
replaced with.  Colors from rows that are unchecked will not be
changed.  Click &ldquo;OK&rdquo; to replace the checked colors.  If
you decide you don't like the result you can always undo your work
(see below).
</p>
<p><b>Note: </b>Currently there is no way to change the color a rare
color will be changed <i>to</i>.  If you're unhappy with the program's
choice, one alternate option is to uncheck that color in the dialog
and then change it by hand using
the <a href="#change_a_color_tool"><i>Change a Color Tool</i></a>.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2">
<h2>Edit Undo/Redo</h2>
<p>
You can undo and redo your edits using the edit
history buttons on the toolbar: undo <img src="leftArrow.png" alt="left arrow icon" /> and
redo <img src="rightArrow.png" alt="right arrow icon" />.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2">
<h2>Gridding and grid color</h2>
<p>
By default all pattern images in this panel have grid lines in black.
You can turn off the grid lines by either clicking the gridlines
button <img src="grid.png" alt="grid icon" /> on the toolbar or by toggling
the <i>Grid</i> menu option in the <i>Image</i> menu.
</p>
<p>
In addition you can change the grid color by selecting <i>Change grid
color</i> from the <i>Image</i> menu.
</p>
<p>
Grid changes apply to all images simultaneously (so, for example, you
can't turn on the grid on the left image and turn it off on the right
image).
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2">
<a name="square_keyboard_shortcuts"></a>
<h2>Keyboard shortcuts</h2>
<p>
You can press "Shift + Left Arrow" (i.e. hold down the shift key and
then press the left arrow key) to make the left image active, "Shift +
Right Arrow" to make the right image active, "Shift + Up Arrow" to
move up in the image list for the active side, and "Shift + Down
Arrow" to move down in the image list for the active side.  The same
shortcuts apply in the color compare panel.
</p>
<p>
See the <a href="overview#overview_keyboard_shortcuts">overview</a> for
application-wide keyboard shortcut information.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2">
<h2>Hiding, Showing, and Deleting Images; Dual Scrolling and Dual zooming</h2>
<p>
Hiding and showing images, deleting images, and dual scrolling and
dual zooming work the same as they do for
the <a href="colorCompare">Color Compare Panel</a>.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2">
<a name="zoom_caveat"></a>
<h2>Zoom to fit, zoom to width, and zoom to height for square images</h2>
<p>
Zoom to fit, zoom to width, and zoom to height may not perform quite
as expected for square images.  For the semi-technical reason, read
on.
</p>
<p>
If a square image is 10 squares wide, then the pixel width of that
image can only ever be a multiple of 10 pixels.  For example, if each
square is 2 pixels wide then the image will be 10*2 = 20 pixels wide,
or if each square is 5 pixels wide then the image will be 10*5 = 50
pixels wide, etc.  If the width available to display that square image
is 58 pixels, the program will display the image using the largest
square size that won't make the resulting image wider than 58 pixels,
which in this case means the square image will be scaled to be 50
pixels wide (leaving a gap of 8 pixels).  The same rule applies to
heights.
</p>
<p>
So square images may appear smaller than you expect them too - if you
really want them larger you can always zoom in.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2">
<h2>Proceeding to the Symbol Editing Panel</h2>
<p>
Once satisfied with the pattern, <b>click on the image you wish to
proceed with</b> to select it (first choosing the Select tool if
necessary) and then click the <i>Pattern</i> button on the toolbar,
which will take you to the <a href="pattern">Symbol Editing
Panel</a>.
</p>

<p>
You can return to this panel, change your options, and click Pattern as
many times as you like.
</p>
</div>
]]></mainBody>

  <outro><![CDATA[]]></outro>

</square>

<!--##################################################################-->

<pattern>

  <title>Pattern</title>

  <intro><![CDATA[]]></intro>

  <mainBody><![CDATA[

<h1 id="pattern" class="section">The Pattern Edit Panel
<img src="pattern_active.png" alt="active pattern icon" /></h1>

<p>
The pattern edit panel allows you to change color symbols and to save
your pattern as a pdf.
</p>
<p>
<b>Note: </b>The pattern view shows a border around each symbol filled
with the color of the corresponding square - this is for on-screen
reference purposes and does not appear in the final pdf version of the
pattern.
</p>

<p> 
<b>Note: </b>The program will attempt to find a program on your
system to automatically view your pdf pattern each time you save.  If
you'd prefer to save without viewing, or if you want to view the pdf but
no viewer is loaded after you save a pdf pattern, or if you'd like to
use a different viewer, then change the viewer settings under
<i>Set pdf viewer</i> in the <i>Help</i> menu (only available in the
Pattern Edit Panel).
</p>

<p> The final pdf includes a title page showing the original image and
the square colored image, then a table illustrating how to piece
together the pattern pages, then a list of symbol/color associations,
then the pattern itself.  Any DMC colors are listed with their DMC
name and code; Anchor colors are listed with their anchor code and the
code/name of the nearest DMC color; for all other colors the code is
the RGB value of the color and the name is the code/name of the
nearest DMC color.  The count column lists the number of times a given
color is used in the pattern.  </p>

<div class="h2Div">
<h2>Choosing Your Image</h2>
<p>
If you have created more than one symboled image (by clicking
the <i>Pattern</i> button on the square edit panel more than once),
you can switch between your images by either selecting the desired
image from the pulldown menu on the toolbar or by choosing it from the
list in the <i>Images</i> menu.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2Div">
<h2>Switching Between the Square and Symbol Views</h2>
<p>
To situate yourself on the symbol image, you can switch back and forth
between the symbol and square color views by clicking the right button
on the image or by clicking the <i>Switch Views</i>
button <img src="switchImages.png" alt="switch images icon" /> on the toolbar.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2Div">
<h2>Using the image previewer</h2>
<p>
Because of the high zoom levels needed to be able to read pattern
symbols on the image, typically only a small portion of the symbol
image will be viewable at any one time.  To help orient yourself and
browse around the image you can use the image previewer in the upper
right corner of the screen.  It provides a smaller view of the entire
image with a red rectangle outlining the area of the symbol image
currently being viewed.  You can move the rectangle, and hence the
region of the symbol image being viewed, by clicking and/or dragging
on the preview image.  To switch between viewing the original image
and the squared image in the preview area, right click anywhere on the
preview image.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2Div">
<h2>Changing a symbol</h2>
<p>
To change the symbol used for a given color, you can either click on
the symbol on the image or right click on the symbol in the symbol
list and choose <i>Change symbol</i>.  In either case you can choose a
new symbol from the symbol selection dialog, which allows you to
select from all remaining available symbols.
</p>

<!--<p>
If a symbol is already in use for a color, you can't select it
directly for use with a different color; instead you can assign the
first color an unused symbol (thereby freeing up the desired symbol)
and then assign the new color the just freed symbol.
</p>-->
</div>

<div class="h2Div">
<h2 id="savePattern">Saving a Pattern to a Pdf File</h2>

<p>
To save your pattern to a pdf, click the <i>To pdf</i> button on the
toolbar.  Before your pattern is saved you'll have the opportunity to
choose the size of the symbols to be used in the pdf as well as to
provide a title and/or any copyright information you'd like to
include.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2Div">
<h2 id="pattern_keyboard_shortcuts">Keyboard shortcuts</h2>
<p>
You can press "Shift + Up Arrow" (i.e. hold down the shift key and
then press the up arrow) to move up in the image list and "Shift +
Down Arrow" to move down in the image list.  The same shortcuts apply
in the color compare and square edit panels.
</p>
<p>
See the <a href="overview#overview_keyboard_shortcuts">overview</a> for
application-wide keyboard shortcut information.
</p>
</div>

<div class="h2Div">
<h2>Gridding and grid color</h2>
<p>
Gridding and grid color are controlled just as for
the <a href="square">square edit panel</a>.
</p>
</div>
]]></mainBody>

  <outro><![CDATA[]]></outro>

</pattern>

<!--##################################################################-->

</root>